## THOMAS MAREK

## **Senior Ruby Web Application Developer**

http://iamthomasmarek.com • hello@iamthomasmarek.com

Ten years of experience designing and developing Web Applications (with five years on Rails applications) including back-end service integration, performance analysis and optimization, complex database models, and state-of-the-art graphical user interfaces. Specialized in agile software development with Kanban and Scrum. Experienced leading a technical team, working remotely and exceeding expectations.

Concepts Agile Development, BDD, Kanban, Scrum, Responsive Design Languages Ruby (5 years), JavaScript (10 years), CoffeeScript (2 year),

Python (9 years), C++ (10 years)

Web Technologies HTML, CSS, XML, JSON, REST, AJAX, WebSockets

Ruby Ecosystem Rails, Sinatra, Middleman, Sidekiq, RSpec, FactoryGirl, Capybara

JavaScript Ecosystem Node.js, jQuery, Underscore.js

Data Stores PostgreSQL, MySQL, MongoDB, CouchDB, Memcached Software RubyMine, Git, Photoshop, Nginx, Phusion Passenger, Puppet

Services AWS, Heroku, Bugsnag, NodePing, New Relic, Google Analytics, Trello

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Part time Lead Developer Lead Developer Web Application Developer uSwitch Ireland, Dublin, Ireland June 2013 - Present April 2013 - May 2013 October 2012 - March 2013

Led the development of <a href="http://www.uswitch.ie">http://www.uswitch.ie</a>, a PPC and SEO driven comparison and switching service for broadband and energy products in Ireland. The last eleven months remotely from Germany and USA.

- Developed a Node.js application, which tracks all user activity and interacts with Google Analytics API, to be able to measure and improve the performance of Google AdWords campaigns.
- Increased SEO traffic by 20% with the creation of dynamic location based landing pages.
- Improved overall site performance by creating a Sinatra web service to prepare and cache Wordpress content for the dynamic integration into landing pages.
- Installed and established a staging environment, which replicates the full production stack, to advance quality and stability of new features.
- Reduced the page load time by 35% through migrating the whole cloud based application stack from USA to Europe, implementing caching on multiple levels and optimising database queries.
- Created a tool with Ruby and Puppet to ease managing our infrastructure hosted on Amazon EC2.
- Boosted our company's productivity and quality of work by supervising our Kanban-style agile workflow and initiating the use of a web-based project management tool.
- · Interviewed and later trained new developers.

Technologies: Rails, Sinatra, Node.js, WordPress, Jekyll, RSpec, Haml, Sass, CoffeeScript, jQuery, PostgreSQL, MySQL, MongoDB, Memcached, AWS, Heroku, Nginx, Puppet, Bugsnag

### **Software Developer**

June 2005 - September 2012

BioSolveIT GmbH, Sankt Augustin, Germany

BioSolveIT is a globally operating scientific software development company providing tools, services, and research collaborations within the areas of drug design.

Most noteworthy among many projects include:

<u>EU-funded Project Open PHACTS:</u> Developed the back-end for <a href="http://www.chembionavigator.org">http://www.chembionavigator.org</a>. The last two months remotely from Dublin.

- Developed a Ruby Gem to communicate with the web services of ChemSpider and the Linked Data Cache API of the OPS Platform. (<a href="http://github.com/openphacts/ops\_gems">http://github.com/openphacts/ops\_gems</a>)
- Established real-time bidirectional server/client communication over WebSockets to speed-up user workflows.
- Built a multithreaded command-line tool to bind internally developed C++ libraries to Ruby back-end services. Tool designed to be highly scalable and resource efficient.
- Integrated a background job system for long running tasks to reduce user wait times.
- Setup a production server including error notification, maintenance mode and staging environment.

*Technologies:* Rails, RSpec, Haml, Sass, ExtJS, MySQL, Apache httpd, Phusion Passenger, HAProxy

Internal Agile Project Management Tool: Managed the full product lifecycle of a Rails Application.

• Leveraged continuous server polling to keep client data up to date thereby preventing parallel write conflicts in a multi-user environment.

Technologies: Rails, RSpec, MySQL, Apache httpd, Phusion Passenger

<u>Internal License Management Tool:</u> Developed a web-based License Management Tool in Python.

 Defined and implemented an Email based API to allow an external application to automatically generate test licenses.

<u>LeadIT:</u> Contributed as a development team-member to the company's main product written in C++ on Qt.

- Mentored junior developers by pair programming and code reviews to boost team performance and improve code quality.
- Scraped and re-engineered the test system to simplify the prevention of regressions and reduce maintenance costs.
- Established an automated process for continuous integration and packaging to improve the software quality and reduce the time to market.

Technologies: Pivotal Tracker, Jenkins

#### ScrumMaster

October 2010 - September 2012

BioSolveIT GmbH, Sankt Augustin, Germany

• Increased our company's productivity and quality of work by initiating and supervising the adoption to agile software development with Scrum.

#### **EDUCATION**

# Professional Training as a Certified Computer Specialist

June 2002 - June 2005

BioSolveIT GmbH, Sankt Augustin, Germany

"Fachinformatiker für Anwendungsentwicklung" - Three-year practical training in a company accompanied by lectures and exams in a vocational training college. The training focused on software development and fundamental economic principles.